<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Julia on Back2Numbers</title>
    <link>/categories/julia.html</link>
    <description>Recent content in Julia on Back2Numbers</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-au</language>
    <copyright>This work is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution-ShareAlike 4.0 International License.</copyright>
    <lastBuildDate>Fri, 31 Jul 2020 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="/categories/julia/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Neural Ordinary Differential Equations</title>
      <link>/2020/07/31/neural-ordinary-differential-equations.html</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 31 Jul 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2020/07/31/neural-ordinary-differential-equations.html</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Presentation at the Kong Kong Machine Learning meetup</title>
      <link>/2020/04/30/presentation-at-the-hong-kong-machine-learning-meetup.html</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 30 Apr 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2020/04/30/presentation-at-the-hong-kong-machine-learning-meetup.html</guid>
      <description>I recently made a presentation at the regular Hong Kong Machine Learning meetup organised by Gautier Marti.
The presentation was an introduction to Julia and used as an example a SEIR model COVID-19 I had written. The presentation is available on Github.
It seems to have had some effect!</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Forecasting the progression of COVID-19</title>
      <link>/2020/03/25/2020-03-25-forecasting-covid-19.html</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 25 Mar 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2020/03/25/2020-03-25-forecasting-covid-19.html</guid>
      <description>The Neherlab COVID-19 forecast model using CSV, Dates; using DataFrames, DataFramesMeta; using Plots, PyPlot; using DifferentialEquations; This is more a data science post than machine learning. It was born after reading a report from Imperial College London and finding a forecasting model by NeherLab. The numbers produced by those models can only be described as terrifying.
How do those models work? How are they calibrated?
BUT
Remember that whatever concerns one can have about their precision, those models are all absolutely clear that social-distancing, quarantining have a massive impact on death rates.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>