<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Back2Numbers</title>
    <link>/</link>
    <description>Recent content on Back2Numbers</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-au</language>
    <copyright>This work is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution-ShareAlike 4.0 International License.</copyright>
    <lastBuildDate>Mon, 15 Jul 2019 21:48:51 -0700</lastBuildDate>
    
        <atom:link href="/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    
        <item>
        <title></title>
        <link>/whoami.html</link>
        <pubDate>Mon, 15 Jul 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        
        <guid>/whoami.html</guid>
        <description>Back2Numbers /whoami.html -


&lt;div id=&#34;whoami---thank-you-gödel-escher-and-bach&#34; class=&#34;section level3&#34;&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;#&amp;gt;whoami - Thank you &lt;em&gt;Gödel, Escher and Bach&lt;/em&gt;!&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My education was completely scientific with a couple of engineering degrees with a particular passion for mathematics. Add to that a life-long fascination for artificial intelligence. I can trace that back to reading a particular birthday present: &lt;em&gt;Gödel, Escher and Bach&lt;/em&gt;. This book held me riveted at 17.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;BUT…&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But travelling and discovering the planet was a powerful magnet that I could not resist and it turned out that banking and finance first gave me that opportunity. Followed about 20 years doing, and enjoying, that in a few countries.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I am now going back to digging into what has happened over those past 20 years in machine and statistical learning.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I am available for &lt;a href=&#34;mailto:Emmanuel.Rialland@gmail.com&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;consulting&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt; and, if there is a great fit, something more permanent. Get in touch and let us have a chat. 5 minutes is all it takes.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You can find more about me on my &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.linkedin.com/in/emmanuelrialland/&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;LinkedIn profile&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
- /whoami.html - This work is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution-ShareAlike 4.0 International License.</description>
        </item>
    
    
  </channel>
</rss> 