<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Machine Learning on Back2Numbers</title>
    <link>/tags/machine-learning.html</link>
    <description>Recent content in Machine Learning on Back2Numbers</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-au</language>
    <copyright>This work is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution-ShareAlike 4.0 International License.</copyright>
    <lastBuildDate>Thu, 31 Dec 2020 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="/tags/machine-learning/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>RNN Compressive Memory Part 3: The Compression algorithm</title>
      <link>/2020/12/31/rnn-compressive-memory-part-3-the-compression-algorithm.html</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 31 Dec 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2020/12/31/rnn-compressive-memory-part-3-the-compression-algorithm.html</guid>
      <description>This is part 3 of a discussion of the DeepMind paper about Compressive Transformers for Long-Range Sequence Modelling.
 Part 1: A high level introduction to Compressive Memory mechanics starting from basic RNNS;
 Part 2 (here): a detailed explanation of the TransformerXL;
 Part 3: an implementation using PyTorch;
 Part 4: finally, its application to time series.
  This post describes the building blocks up to what makes a TransformerXL model as presented in June 2019.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>RNN Compressive Memory Part 2: The TransformerXL</title>
      <link>/2020/12/30/rnn-compressive-memory-part-2-the-transformerxl.html</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 30 Dec 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2020/12/30/rnn-compressive-memory-part-2-the-transformerxl.html</guid>
      <description>This is part 2 of a discussion of the DeepMind paper about Compressive Transformers for Long-Range Sequence Modelling.
 Part 1: A high level introduction to Compressive Memory mechanics starting from basic RNNS;
 Part 2 (here): more details about the TransformerXL;
 Part 3: an implementation using PyTorch (soon);
 Part 4: finally, its application to time series (soon).
  This post describes the building blocks up to what makes a TransformerXL model as presented in June 2019.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Neural Ordinary Differential Equations</title>
      <link>/2020/07/31/neural-ordinary-differential-equations.html</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 31 Jul 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2020/07/31/neural-ordinary-differential-equations.html</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Presentation at the Kong Kong Machine Learning meetup</title>
      <link>/2020/04/30/presentation-at-the-hong-kong-machine-learning-meetup.html</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 30 Apr 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2020/04/30/presentation-at-the-hong-kong-machine-learning-meetup.html</guid>
      <description>I recently made a presentation at the regular Hong Kong Machine Learning meetup organised by Gautier Marti.
The presentation was an introduction to Julia and used as an example a SEIR model COVID-19 I had written. The presentation is available on Github.
It seems to have had some effect!</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>RNN Compressive Memory Part 1: A high level introduction.</title>
      <link>/2020/03/07/rnn-compressive-memory-part-1.html</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 07 Mar 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2020/03/07/rnn-compressive-memory-part-1.html</guid>
      <description>This is the first post of series dedicated to Compressive Memory of Recurrent Neural Networks. This is inspired by a recent DeepMind paper published in November 2019 on Arxiv.
Currently, the ambition of the series is to follow this plan:
 Part 1 (here): A high level introduction to Compressive Memory mechanics starting from basic RNNS;
 Part 2: a detailed explanation of the TransformerXL;
 Part 3: an implementation using PyTorch (soon);</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>HarvardX Gitbooks available</title>
      <link>/2019/12/12/harvardx-gitbooks-available.html</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 12 Dec 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2019/12/12/harvardx-gitbooks-available.html</guid>
      <description>Both capstones for the HarvardX certificates are now available. Just click on the links!
If Gitbooks are not your thing, at the top of their main page, there is a download link to a pdf version.
They make for a good knock-me-asleep reading…</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>HarvardX Final Report - LendingClub dataset</title>
      <link>/2019/12/11/harvardx-final-report-lendingclub-dataset.html</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 11 Dec 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2019/12/11/harvardx-final-report-lendingclub-dataset.html</guid>
      <description>After 3 months of work, the final report for the HarvardX Data Science course was submitted.
It is based on the LendingClub dataset. LendingClub is a peer-2-peer lender. This is a matching of private borrowers and investors. Small amounts, fairly high risk (if they could, borrowers would probably have had a bank involved). Surprisingly, after tapping a market of individual lenders, the biggest lenders are now the banks. To inform the investors, LendingClub make historical information publicly available.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Quick Thought: Universal translator and same language translator</title>
      <link>/2019/10/25/quick-idea-universal-translator-and-same-language-translator.html</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 25 Oct 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2019/10/25/quick-idea-universal-translator-and-same-language-translator.html</guid>
      <description>Quick Thoughts are random thoughts looking for comments
 Let’s imagine a universal translator able to translate any language to any language. Sourcing a corpus of pair translation is a major hurdle. However there is an almost infinite corpus of pair translations: a language with itself; translating English to English is easy, even for a computer.
Let’s give the blackbox universal translator three inputs: a source text, the language of the source text, the language of the desired translation.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Neural Network - Incremental Growth </title>
      <link>/2019/10/23/neural-network-incremental-growth.html</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 23 Oct 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2019/10/23/neural-network-incremental-growth.html</guid>
      <description>|  | DRAFT 1  | This post is first and foremost asking for assistance. Is anything blatantly incorrect? If not, can anybody point to existing articles/posts/litterature?
We all have laptops. But le’ts face it, even in times of 32GB of RAM and NVMe2 drives, forget about running any interesting TensorFlow model. You need to get an external GPU, build your own rig, or very quickly pay a small fortune for cloud instances.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Stanford Online - Machine Learning C229 </title>
      <link>/2019/08/02/stanford-online-machine-learning-c229.html</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 02 Aug 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2019/08/02/stanford-online-machine-learning-c229.html</guid>
      <description>Review I recently completed the Stanford online version of the Machine Learning CS229 course taught by Andrew Ng. There is no need to introduce this course which has reached stardom.
It often was a trip a trip down memory lane repeating what I studied in the late 90’ies. It was interesting that quite a bit has remained as relevant. Back then, and I am now talking early 90ies, neural networks were still fashionable but computationally intractable past what would hardly be considered a single layer nowadays.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>